to force. No child would have access to
social media. Of course, I'm not going
to say that. But I do believe it's the
right thing to do. I do believe we can
enforce it. I think we'll be better at
enforcing it actually having learned
from the Australian model and having
learned from our own experience with the
online safety act. So, I genuinely think
we can enforce it, but I'm not prepared
to say that because some children may
try to get around it and some may get
around it. That is not a good reason to
take the act of banning. I just don't
accept that. Um I'm afraid. Um Beth from
Sky.
>> Thank you, Prime Minister. Beth Rigby,
Sky News. Um you say that you won't
compromise on the happiness of children,
but you also know that US big tech will
hate this ban. Are you concerned about
how President Trump might react to this
when you see him at the G7 and the
consequences for the UK? and you're
announcing this ma in a major week where
you could in days face a leadership
challenge. Does this ban set your legacy
and under are there any circumstances in
which you might step aside? Thank you
very much.
>> Uh well be thank you for packing I think
two or three questions into one. Um look
let let me take them in turn on the US
big tech. But of course um this is about
um fighting for what we think is right
and I think that protecting children is
right now on US big tech on tech here.
I'm a fan of tech and AI. I think it has
got huge capability to change our world
for the better. Um and that's why I made
a very pro tech and AI speech last
Monday in fact at London Tech Week. I'm
all in favor of that. I do not accept
and I will never accept that you can't
be both pro tech and AI and at the same
time say we must protect our children.
In fact, when I look at the brilliance
of the innovators in AI and tech, I know
very well that it is possible to do
both. Um the innovation is incredible in
AI and what is going on. Don't tell me
that it's impossible for those
innovators, those people who are
brilliant at technology, to devise the
ways to protect our children. And I
think we should. I So I think you can be
pro- um AI and tech, which I am, but at
the same time protecting our children,
which I am. The two are not uh
incompatible. Uh they're not mutually
exclusive. I think they go together. And
actually I think uh talking to the big
tech companies they know very well um
that they and all of us have a
responsibility to protect children. Um
and so I don't see uh I'm not saying
there aren't conversations to be had
Beth. I think there will be but I
genuinely think that we can be both pro
tech and AI and at the same time protect
our children and we will protect our
children. It's a red line for me. I'm
never going to accept the argument that
for the future of AI and tech, we must
leave our children exposed in the way
that they have been or they might be in
the future. I'll never accept that
argument. And I don't think the vast
majority of people in this country would
um would say so. In relation to um the
legacy issues, I I see this differently.
This is a huge issue for the country. Uh
this isn't about any one individual. It
is something which people in this room
have been um concerned about uh living
with and campaigning about for years and
I think we do them and all those who've
been concerned about this a disservice
to try to um put that into um you know a
particular week when there's a
bi-election. That's not what it's about.
This is a huge this is a statement of
our values who we are as a country um
and it's a way of actually bringing our
country together. So for me, this is
bigger than some of the usual two and
fros of politics, although there's
plenty of that. Uh, thank you, Beth.
Chris Hope from GB News.
>> A lot of children are watching your your
speech right now over our breakfast
show. Will you be finding them if they
go on social media? What's what's the
jeopardy for them? And just quickly,
what this means for freedom of speech?
Is it the thin end of the wedge? Will a
future government use the powers you're
bringing in to ban people they don't
like from social media?
>> Well, Chris, firstly, the enforcement
will be on the platform providers, not
on the children. I think it's really
important that we uh make that clear.
We're not going to start taking action
against 13 and 14 and 15 year olds um
who are trying as they always will to
get around rules that adults put in
their path. So this is absolutely aimed
at those that are providing the
circumstance the the platform on the
question of free speech. I mean let's be
straight and honest about this.
How many people in this room are
prepared to defend adult strangers
contacting children online
and we know what happens um when that uh
develops into the sort of abuse and
worse. How many people are prepared to
stand up and say that's free speech and
I wouldn't do anything about it any more
than you'd say um we wouldn't take
measures to stop that happening in the
offline world. I think it's
extraordinary that somehow we've got
ourselves to a position where until now
we've shrugged our shoulders. I
genuinely think it's difficult to think
in what circumstances any of us would
put our children into a place where they
could have uh where unknown adults could
have access to them without us knowing
anything about it onetoone. We wouldn't
do it. Um so it's not about free speech.
It's about basic protection of children.
And to take other examples, Chris, look,
I'm a great advocate of free speech. I
really am. But sending sexually explicit
pictures to and from children
That's not free speech. That's basic
protection. It's got nothing to do with
technology. We have protected our
children from that sort of harm for
years in this country. We're right to do
so. What we're doing now is making sure
that it's fit for purpose in the world
we actually live in. Thank you very
much. Um Chris, I hope that satisfies
some of the children or young people who
are watching uh on your program. Um and
it'd be very interesting to see their
reaction. I've got Natasha from LBC.
Natasha.
>> Hi, Prime Minister. Thank you. Um, LBC
has heard from so many parents who want
to see this change, but what does
success look like to you? How will you
make sure that this is actually
enforced? And just to follow up on
Beth's question, how will you explain
this policy to a skeptical President
Trump who may not support your move?
Thank you.
>> Um, just in terms of success, um, that
will be, um, in a drop off in children
on social media. it won't be complete
because some of them will get around it.
Um but a massive drop off in children on
social media is sort of uh step number
one. I think step number two
probably equally if not more important
is a cultural change. A sense that our
children can grow up differently
um and have better and more enriching
childhoods as a result. Now that will
take a bit longer. I think um there will
be a almost a transition because a lot
of teenagers under the age of 16 have
already started growing up with social
media. But as the expectation changes
over time as it will um I think that
there will be a cultural change.
Cultural change is always much harder
than you can changing the law is one
thing can be very difficult. Cultural
change is much much um harder. in
relation to um President Trump. Um look
um I I I honestly think that um across
world leaders there has always been a
recognition that um leaders have to take
steps to protect children. I don't think
that's controversial. There will always
be arguments as to exactly what the
limits of that are um and what rules
should be in place. Um but I don't see
that as a as a as a problem. Um and
obviously um we're about to go off to
the G7 later on um today and I will
discuss this with world leaders when I'm
there. Thank you very much Natasha. I've
got Sophie from the Mirror.
So
>> thank you Prime Minister. Um so I wanted
to ask about Ian Russell. As you know,
the dad of Molly Russell, he's against a
ban. He says that he feels desperately
let down by you, that you're rushing a
ban, and that fundamentally under this
package, a dangerous digital landscape
will still exist. What's your response
to this? And also you haven't mentioned
anything about the cliff edge for 16
year olds. Will we get an overnight
curfew for 16 and 17 year olds? Thank
you.
>> Yeah, let me start if I may with Ian
Russell and just express my highest
respect for Ian. I've had the
opportunity to talk this through with
him on a number of occasions, including
just a few weeks ago. I have the highest
regard and highest respect for him and
his views. um and um I've heard them
firsthand from him and I understand how
deeply he is concerned about and I
obviously do also uh recognize um he's
been through an experience I haven't
been through and um I have to
acknowledge that and have to be humbled
by that. Um, frankly, um, I do know that
he's concerned that, um, simply banning
and not taking on some of the platform
providers to make sure they provide age
appropriate content is in his view not
quite the right way of doing that. I do
understand that. I think in a way the
ban does a bit of both because it bans
with clarity which I do think parents
want but it also um uh we've got
additional um measures that we're taking
for under 16s and under 18s in relation
to stranger engagement live streaming
etc with which is intended to get at
some of the features that are of
concern. on on the question of rushing.
Look, I don't believe this to be rushed.
Um people have expressed different
views. At the beginning of the
consultation, some people said, "Why are
you consulting? You don't need the
evidence. Um just make a decision
without the evidence." I don't agree
with that. Um but and therefore I
thought it was time it was right that we
had um the consultation. not just the
consultation but actually the
conversation that went with it, the
sharing of experiences, the sharing of
views, I think has been an important
part of it. Um, and now we've gone
carefully through that and reached a
conclusion. I think that's the right way
um to do it. But I don't want anything
in my answer to be in any way
disrespectful to Ian um or others that
hold a different view, particularly
those that have lost a child. I don't
think that's right um for me. So I, you
know, it is possible to deeply respect
someone and their views, but to come to
a different conclusion, but we will
continue to work with Ian and others um
on how we make this um work. Um in
relation to the um cliff edge, there are
measures here for uh 16 and 17 year
olds. So it's not quite the cliff edge.
Um there is then the provisions for 16
and 17 year olds uh that we are um
proposing to take um forward. Um but in
the end um whenever you have an age
limit on anything there will always be a
point at which you're beyond the age
that is restricted. Um drink is another
example. Keep coming back to it. But
there are examples where there are
things you can't do till you're age X.
uh then when you can do it um then
obviously um in that sense there's a um
there's a there's a cut off point but I
don't think that should be a reason not
to do this um but I do think it is a
reason to look very carefully at what
more needs to be done for 16 and 17 year
olds so there sort of a graduated um
edge if you like um thank you very much
uh let me go to um Sophia from the sun
>> thank you prime minister um you spoke
about social media intruding too much
into our lives nowadays. Um nowadays you
get a lot of child influencers and
family influences where the the content
of children is used sort of for clicks
and things like that. I wondered is that
something that you are personally
worried about that level of exposure for
children nowadays? Um and prior to the
G7 have you spoken to Donald Trump about
your ban on social media? Um just uh
taking those uh separately,
the the concern that's the heart of this
ban is um social media particularly
um the addictive nature of it and the
and the services that are likely to be
in scope of the ban. They're not um um
dissimilar to those in Australia,
although I think um ours possibly go a
bit further. Certainly I hope that on
the enforcement side um we will do
better than that. Um it doesn't mean
that there isn't any content a child can
ever see on a screen. Um because there
are obvious examples. Um for example,
schools often use screens for homework
purposes. Um and so we've got to have a
sort of common sense approach in
relation to that. But when it comes to
the ban on social media and the features
that we know are harmful uh to children
that don't make them happy and don't
make them safe, that is where we've
drawn the line and that's what this ban
is all about. And in relation to
President Trump, I spoke to him on
Saturday. I'll see him again um this
afternoon. And yes, of course, we'll
discuss this and uh many other issues
and lots of other leaders are very
interested in it. I've had um contact
with other leaders in the course of the
last few days um because many countries
are grappling with this issue which is
how do we keep our children safe online.
It's not a it's not a particularly
um uh issue that relates only to the UK.
You've seen other countries grappling
with it. I think there will be a coming
together of um leaders political
thinking here as um countries will want
to learn just as we wanted to learn from
Australia and go and uh explore how far
they'd got other countries I think will
be now looking to the UK uh to see
whether that doesn't provide a blueprint
uh for them and I hope it does because
um I want children to be safe whatever
country they live in. Uh thank you very
much. I've got Joe from uh Bloomberg.
>> Prime Minister Joe Ma from Bloomberg. On
the situation in the Middle East, if I
may, uh there are many false dawns in
the talks between the US and Iran. So,
how confident are you that this time is
for real? And we haven't seen any
details of this peace agreement. What
details would need to be in a peace
agreement for you to support it?
>> Yes. Um I do think this agreement is
significant.
Um and I I acknowledge that there's been
a lot of discussion uh in recent weeks
where it looked like there might be
agreement and then there wasn't quite an
agreement etc. This is an agreement. I
do think it's significant. Um and I did
discuss it with President Trump on
Saturday specifically and so um I want
to do everything that I can. I want to
work with other world leaders to make
sure that this works. Now obviously um
nothing is guaranteed but it is I think
a significant breakthrough a very
significant breakthrough hopefully um
something which as we work together we
can turn into that enduring peace that
we all want to see. You will know that
we took preparatory action as a
coalition of uh countries led by myself
and President Macron um to put together
um those countries that are prepared to
do some of the reassurance work that's
needed when we get to a moment like this
to help get vessels through the straight
of Hammuz. Um we've got military
planning behind that. So I hope now we
can play our part um in relation to
that. So um I don't you know I I do
think this time it's significant. I do
think it's very important and I think it
is vital that we all put our shoulder to
the wheel. Um now nothing is guaranteed
but this um coming together now is the
best way to ensure that we get the peace
that we all need and also limit the
impact on our economies including here
in the United Kingdom. So that's what
we'll be discussing uh quite intensively
I suspect over the next few days um at
the G7 um starting from the moment we
arrive this afternoon. Thank you very
much Joe. I've got Jim from the FT.
>> Jim Picard, Financial Times. Prime
Minister, um you spoke about some of the
devastating tragedies involving young
people and social media. But beyond
that, there's been an epidemic of mental
health problems in this country over the
last decade or so involving young people
and their mental health issues. This
seems to have begun about a decade ago.
The use of smartphones began about a
decade ago. Do you think the two things
are connected or do you think it's all
just a coincidence? Thank you. I
>> I think there is a correlation. Um,
obviously establishing hard evidence is
always difficult, but I do think there's
a correlation. Um, I think, um, it
became particularly intense during
COVID. Um, and I think we've all seen a
cohort of young people, children, young
people who live through COVID who have
struggled perhaps a little more than
others. I'm very concerned about that.
I'm very concerned about the number of
young people with mental health issues
who are not in work. um we've got a
record number and it's really important
that uh we do everything we can to give
them the support that they need. So I am
concerned about that. I think everybody
is concerned um about it. So I'd say
there's correlation. I'd say there's
particular um added issue in relation to
the COVID um period for children and
young people. Our job now is to act on
that. The ban today um is an important
um part of acting on that, but it's not
the only part. Thank you, Jim. I've got
uh Georgia.
>> Prime Minister, I welcome your changes
today and I think they're absolutely
amazing and for under 16s, it's so
important. But when a young boy does
turn 16, the online misogyny is still
going to be there waiting for him. And
for women, it can take years to get
justice. And that's if it even comes at
all. So I want to know beyond protecting
children from the culture, how do you
plan on changing the culture itself?
>> Yeah, look um Georgia, thank you very
much and and can I just acknowledge the
work that you've done in relation to
violence against women and girls and the
leading part that you have um played. Um
I think the ban can help but you're
absolutely right um to say there need to
be other measures around it and misogyny
is a is a huge problem particularly for
young boys. We've doing a lot of work at
our violence against women and girls
strategy in relation to um that how we
tackle that. Some of the others measures
that we've taken outside of today's
announcements in relation to the ability
to pass and receive sexually explicit
images for example I think is hugely
important. It's not the only thing but
it is an important part of this buildup
to misogyny. There's a huge amount more
that we need to do and we are doing
that's through the violence against
women and girls strategy and I look
forward to working with you on it. Thank
you Georgia. And I've got Allison.
Allison Perry.
>> Allison Perry, content creator and
podcaster. Um, Prime Minister, parents
have spent years feeling like we're
fighting this battle alone. Uh, beyond
restricting the access with this ban,
what practical help are you going to be
offering parents who are trying to raise
children in a world dominated by
smartphones and social media?
>> Well, Allison, thank you for raising
that. do think that um the ban is a
really important step but there's got to
be stuff around it and I think that is
working with parents I think working
with schools as well we need to think
about how this fits within the uh school
curriculum how children learn about
technology and AI and social media
because the mere fact that we're banning
it from under 16 which we will doesn't
mean we don't need to teach children
about social media because they're going
to be exposed to it um when they're past
16 or then again when they're past 18.
Therefore, whether it's working with
parents or working with schools, we need
to do the necessary work. I think that
will also be part of the culture change
that we need to bring about in relation
to social media. So, you're absolutely
right. There's more work that needs to
be done around this. But what today is
is a really important, clear, and
decisive step uh to ban children from
social media um under the age of 16. And
I do I do think that uh the vast
majority of people across the country
will welcome that. Thank you all very
much indeed. Thank you.